Inventory of the Mildred Stead Capron papers, 1931-1972
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Mildred Stead Capron papers
1931-1972
Capron, Mildred Stead
03470
8.41 cubic ft. (19 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Mildred Stead Capron Papers contain the adventure documentary films she created. Included are related materials including production files, research notes, publicity, and photographs.
Biography of Mildred Stead Capron
Mildred Stead Capron (1899-1978) was a photographer, author, and member of the Society of Women Geographers, 1955-1978. Her publications included: "Wyoming Indians, Describing the Work of the Episcopal Church in Wyoming amongst the Shoshone and Arapaho Tribes" (1944) and "Prayers at Christmas" (1944). After arriving in Wyoming in 1935, she lived on the Arapaho Reservation. She lived in Moose, Wyoming in Teton County where she operated Capron Film Productions on the Murie Ranch. She corresponded with the noted photographer, Maragaret Bourke-White, 1963-1971. She was a friend of Mardy and Olaus Murie, noted Wyoming conservationists whose views she shared.
Scope and Content
The Mildred Stead Capron Papers consist of the 16mm adventure documentary films she made during the 1950s and 1960s. The areas she documented in the United States include Wyoming, Alaska, and the Chesapeake Bay. International sites include Ireland, Brittany in northwest France, Portugal, the islands of Azores and Madeira, Spain, and South Africa. Also included are the film production files. These include scripts, research notes, subject files, photographs and negatives, and advertising for her documentaries. The collection also includes a small amount of biographical material and some of her personal photographs. Most of the photographs relate to Wyoming landscapes and wildlife in the areas of the Snowy Range, the Wind River Range, Jackson Hole, the National Elk Refuge, the Teton Mountains, and wild horse roundups in the Red Desert. Other photographs relate to sheep shearing, a pow wow on the Wind River Indian Reservation, and outdoor recreation scenes.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Mildred Stead Capron at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Mildred Capron (1970-1971), Donald Murie (1978), and the Murie Center of Moose, Wyoming (2004, 2006).
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at http://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu:8180/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~95~95.
Access Terms
Capron Film Productions.; Women photographers-- United States-- 20th century.; Arapaho Indians-- Missions-- Wyoming.; Shoshoni Indians-- Missions-- Wyoming.; Travelogues (Motion pictures, television, etc.)
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Native Americans; Expeditions and Adventure; Social Life and Customs; Wyoming; Moving Images
Container List
- Series I. Biographical Information and Personal Notes
  This series includes biographical material, personal notes, and photographs of Mildred Capron. The material is contained in one folder.
  - Biographical Material and Personal Notes, undated, 1936-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Production Files
  This series contains the production files for Capron’s 16mm films. Included are script notes, technical data, research notes, subject files, advertising and publicity, and photographs and negatives of the sites she visited. The files are arranged alphabetically by title of film.
  - Alaskan Summer, undated, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Deep Roots in the Chesapeake, undated, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Deep Roots in the Chesapeake, undated, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Ireland: A Living Tapestry, undated, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Ireland: A Living Tapestry, undated, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Sky High in Wyoming, undated, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Solo Safari to South Africa, 1951-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Solo Safari to South Africa, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Spell of Brittany, undated, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Spell of Brittany, undated, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Ten Islands of Lost Legends: Madeira and the Azores, undated, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Ten Islands of Lost Legends: Madeira and the Azores, undated, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - This Is Portugal, undated, 1957-1961 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Series III. Photographs
  This series contains photographs taken by Mildred Capron. Most of the photographs are of Wyoming landscapes, wildlife, and outdoor recreation. Some images are of her world travels.
  - Photographs – Kleiber, Hans, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Jackson Hole, Grand Teton National Park, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Outdoor Recreation Scenes, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Sheep Shearing Operations, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Slides of Various Scenes (including coal mining, the Medicine Wheel, Green River Lakes, sheep wagons, snow plows, and Oregon Trail ruts.), undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photographs –Wyoming – Wild Horse Roundup in the Red Desert, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Wildlife and Landscapes, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Wind River Indian Reservation Pow Wow, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photographs – Wyoming – Wind River Range (includes images of pack horses), undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Photo Scrapbook (includes Laramie, winter scenes in Jackson Hole, and international scenes), undated (Box 7)
  - Photo Scrapbook of 1931 trip to Japan and China, undated, 1931, 1934 (Box 8)
  - Photo Scrapbook (includes wild horse roundup in Red Desert, Jackson Hole and Grand Teton National Park, Yosemite, Glacier National Park, and international scenes), undated (Box 9)
  - Oversize Photographs – Wyoming Wildlife and Landscapes, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Photograph – Miscellaneous Scenes (U.S. and International scenes), undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Negatives of Madeira and South Africa, undated (Box 11)
  - Negatives of Portugal, undated (Box 12)
  - Negatives of Cape Cod, undated (Box 13)
  - Negatives of Ireland, undated (Box 14)
- Series IV. Motion Picture Films and Audiotapes
  This series contains the full-length feature films produced by Capron. Additionally, film clips, short takes, and audio reel-to-reel tapes used in the making of her films are included. Some audio relates to music on the Wind River Indian Reservation.
  - 16mm motion picture film (short-takes, and film clips for her productions), undated (Box 15)
  - Reel to Reel Audiotape used for her productions (includes material for Sky High in Wyoming including Wolf Dance and Sun Dance drumming and Indian chanting.), undated (Box 15)
  - Deep Roots in the Chesapeake (full length film), undated (Box 16)
  - Ireland: A Living Tapestry (full length film), undated (Box 16)
  - Sky High in Wyoming (full length film), undated (Box 17)
  - Solo Safari to South Africa (full length film), undated (Box 17)
  - Spell of Brittany (full length film), undated (Box 18)
  - Ten Islands of Lost Legends: Madeira and Azores (full length film), undated (Box 18)
  - Spell of Brittany (film), undated (Box 19)